any such view well to the extent that
you still emphasizing the sense
objects one way or the other s sound
smelt touches that you emphasize them in
terms of you
think at least to some extent suffering
comes from them is caused by them to
that extent you lack
Yara so then if your whole view revolves
around pure management cover up
denial uh of sense objects because
obviously they bother you seemingly you
don't know the escape from them so you
just try to deny the reality of them
through these kind of as I said
retroactive interpr reinterpretations
and like oh see that time when I
suffered because somebody said something
well it was just sound entering my ear
that suffering was not real so you
relieve yourself from the burden of
carrying it because you don't know the
escape from it and you don't really
relieve yourself you just cover it up
until it comes back until the new sounds
touch your ear and then you try so hard
that when somebody's saying something
upsetting to you to interpret that as
sounds touching your ear but your
feelings they don't work that way so
you're going to still be upset even if
the next millisecond you manage to plug
it the the DOA still comes first and the
whole thing the only reason you need to
do all of that is cuz deep down you know
that you cannot not be touched by Dua in
the first place you can only try and
manage it and sort of contain it
but the idea of no this thing that
bothers me can I reach the place where
I'm not
bothered to begin with even if I don't
do anything even if I don't make any
effort to look at it this way or that
way or Focus like this and concentrate
like that and then you real oh that's
where the D
Begins the complete
uprooting and in order to like somebody
who has been metad and some everybody
would have been managing the suffering
to some
extent if you want to start practicing
the practice of uprooting first thing
you need to give up is management of
suffering yeah well seeing at least
you're dependent on that management and
then and then work out work your way
towards being able to basically give it
up because for as long as you don't give
it up you you're not starting practice
you're enslaved by it
yeah yeah the practice is just kept at
the arms
length cuz each time you give into
management you're fueling it you fuel
the the the implicit the tcid assumption
that suffering did come from that thing
that I'm
managing not from my attitude towards
it so that's why Yar it's not just like
one of the random things that anybody
can just do cuz people might develop
that no ah Y is one of the factors for
the Right View okay so how do I do yis
and then I find the right instruction
and then I get the right view well you
do only so by giving up the management
even even
before yeah so you see a snake and
there's like this here so it's like the
first thing is to like not try and get
rid of that just acknowledge well yeah
like the what we were speaking yesterday
like the common notion is you see a
snake there is
fear then you either try to find more
information about snake so to not be
afraid or deny it was a snake to begin
with oh look it was actually just a
rope and then the fear disappears and
you think you you're free now but if you
have a even like a slight degree of of
transparency and honesty yes the fear
might have subsided now cuz you learned
the snake is not venomous or you came
closer and saw that snake was a rope
actually but then you realize yeah okay
but does that mean that I will never in
the future experience anything else that
will make me afraid first even if I can
manage it afterwards and you realize
that that is already a problem cuz what
if you come closer and it's actually
even worse snake than you thought it was
and it's not a
rope then you will be twice as effective
with your fear that already affected you
or just anything that can evoke fear
exactly fact that there is fear exactly
so the fact that you're liable to it
even if you could prove it wrong
afterwards doesn't make it less real
when it affects
you so the D is not there to disapprove
uh disprove reality of
things as a as a way of pasting this
view on everything that bothers you the
D is there to teach you how not to be
bothered in the first place and then you
don't care if it's a real snake or a
rope or a venomous or non-venomous one
you won't be affected by fear either
way and that's the true
Freedom not just knowing how to cover it
up so that's like if somebody were to
start sense restraint keeping the
precepts rightly
not not paid with the view of oh if I
just do these things mechanically I'll
become a sop but more like as we
discussed for last few days
here when you say no to your desires
when the precepts restrain you the Mind
complains you don't cover it up you
don't give in you don't psychologize and
you certainly don't try to get rid of it
but you you already will be covering up
it's more like seeing that you're
covering up so basically by when I say you're not
up so basically by when I say you're not
covering it up your starting point your
starting point is covering it up exactly
but now you know that you're not
supposed to covering up so you begin to
cover it up less and less and less until
it's completely uncovered but what I'm
saying is that even at that stage doing
that is closer to yasara it's closer to
that right way of attending things for
what they are where they are then doing
the Yar on account of you learn what Yar
is and now you're trying to attend
things in this different in uh indirect
way peripherally and so
on so through through not allowing
yourself a cover up you are doing the
practice you're doing the Yar which
means it cannot be done the way you
conceive doing to
be and that's why the the more you do it
the more effortless it becomes because
actually there was never effort required
effort was required in covering it up
then effort might be required in in
abstaining from covering it up until
it's sufficiently
uncovered because you realize like
sensuality following desire factually
takes effort and takes
time restraining from it is immediately
visible and takes no effort and takes no
time saying no to desire that you didn't
follow that's it it ended
there you you're restrained so you don't
have to like do it keep doing it or
start engaging in the actions in order
to do it you just need to abstain from
going down the effort of sensuality that
would take time and immediately stay
with what was already there like right
now there's already sight sounds smells
taste touches thoughts that don't
involve crav there not it's not like
that I need to try and no yeah but what
person needs to do is start to see them
correctly in other words recognize
sense objects sight sounds melt this
touches they are not affected with
craving existing on their own within the
domains of the senses and then recognize
those that are rooted in craving and
they're not giv to those but you don't
have to deny every sight because if that
were the case then the Buddha would have
agreed with that man who said how do you
practice you know Taming of your eye he
says by not seeing forms with my eyes
and he says well that's like a blind
man so it's not not all of the SES that
are a problem if you think all of the
SES are a problem means you don't see
the difference between SES affected with
craving and SES not effective craving
which means you don't see the middle
way and for as long as that's not
discerned there is no practice for that
person it's the same even with virtue in
terms of
the what you're saying about it taking
no effort and taking no time yeah that
you can see that same princi on the
level of like it's only like an act
think you know need to think of it as an
active practice that you need to do for
as long as
your mode of existence I suppose is
still like dependent on very specific
actions that most of the time even most
people are not doing yeah you realize
okay I just need to kind of stay on this
on this level that's already kind of
there without any without any fuel is
required exactly and that's
point but isn't the case that this
recognition of those
pressures are more like more gradual so
you're unable
to right now right here just release all
the possible pressure pressures but it's
like one step ahead so there's a bunch
of presses so to speak and they begin to
cease so to speak
cease no definitely gradual the whole
thing is
gradual you cannot do it just all
instantly all together that's why it has
to start with physical restraint and and
restraining your senses so even if you
don't see any of this it that's why it
has well because you don't see any of
this that that's the starting point a
person needs to
um say no to unsuitable sight sounds
smell taste touches even if they don't
see the reason
why they don't see a direct connection
between saying no to those things and
practicing the dhama they have to at
least start saying no first in order to
see the connection with the practice of
the dam and that connection would
gradually well be become revealed be
revealed like uncor the Mind properly
sorry anchored anchored the properly
well that would be the result of it it
wouldn't be your
doing you would anchor the Mine by not
basically exposing it to the
waves then it would
settle but you can't just put the anchor
down and now it's anchored while you're
still fully allowing it to go among the
high waves
also not forgetting that that this
anchor you so to speak you
already your mind is already developed
to some degree mhm but sometimes you can
I don't know forget or too much go into
the senses is it possible so well you
senses is it possible so well you
achieve
some development forgetting about it
it's not a problem in
itself but acting against it
through giving in the acts of Desire ill
will distraction that's what makes it a
distraction that's what makes it a
problem and those things you cannot you
don't do accidentally they cannot just
happen or you just forgot and you
slipped into them they're always on the
level of your
choice CU it's important to to
distinguish this because if people don't
see that that's where the threshold is
then they'll be afraid of naturally just
mind forgetting stuff that's just and
and that's impossible to stop things
come and go you can't possibly know
everything all the time even the Buddha
said that nobody even the the Supreme
Tata is not omniscient that he knows
everything at every second all the
time that's not how things work and
that's not the problem but if people
don't know that the problem is choices
of greed diversion delusion and they
have not uh discerned them sufficient
enough then they'll fear everything and
nothing so then when they forget
about anchoring of the mind or the
greater context they break the precepts
because there's nothing in between that
they learn how to
see but even then even when you're the
utmost forgetful one when it comes to
Breaking the precepts or doing un
wholesome things that still has to be a
conscious choice so if you still go against the
choice so if you still go against the
precepts and you still break that Cho go
through that choice to break it means
you haven't really um understood
the weight of that action you haven't
understood the danger of doing so for
yourself so that's why one breaks
precepts not because they're
forgetful because if something becomes
very important to you doesn't matter if
it's a millisecond or or two
hours the importance of it remains and
you can't forget it as I was giving that
similar with a drinking a a beautiful
beverage that then you find out there is
poison in
it I mean the beverage is so good you're
addicted to it let's put it that way
you've been drinking it your whole life
and now somebody says there's a poison
in it and you kind of can see for
yourself that there probably is a poison
in
it the only time you would drink the
beverage is if you completely forget
that there is a poison in it which means
you haven't really understood the danger
of the poison
or sometimes you might uh not know how
harmful the poison is cuz you haven't
investigated enough and you know there
is a poison but you think you'll be fine
you know every now and
then and that's why you would choose to
drink it
again but if on the other hand you
realized to the extent necessary the
danger of the poison doesn't matter if
somebody wakes you in the middle wakes
you up in the middle of the night if you
don't remember anything else drink means
poison poison means
death and you wouldn't need to go
through the motions to remind yourself
how not to choose to drink it you just
need to remind you just need to
basically get see that danger that you
would have developed by then and you
wouldn't be drinking it the similar the
Buddha gave is like the the man um the
leper who was used to burning his skin
with with coal and
cuz he was offering him a relief but
then he finds another medicine his skin
is cured no more leprosy would he still
burn himself with those painful CS no
says even if two strong men were to take
him under his arm and and drag him into
the into the pit of Embers he would want
to be everywhere else anywhere else
except there he wouldn't need to like he
wouldn't be able to accidentally choose
the Embers again because they're
factually unpleasant
any any other perception other than the
perception other than the perception of
the adct addicted poison that you've
been
drinking but as I said you can't
mechanically just think these impersonal
abstract thoughts and then magically the
choice of choosing the drink disappears
cuz that's not where the choice was was
coming from the choice was coming from
not recognizing fully that it will kill
you if you drink it as simple as
that so then the practice is to
contemplate the danger that it is
implicit until it really sinks in that
it will kill you if you drink it then
you can't forget it even if if you if
you forget everything else you cannot
possibly intentionally engage with it
ever again
example a little bit in different
direction for then let's say that one
already see the senses at the senses but
sometimes they pressure more and
sometimes they like a more com mhm and
there is
this like knowledge that this pressure
of from the
senses and it's more intense yeah and
this is the time when
one breaking the precept so to speak
because this well more int pressure no
see the pressure can be as intense as it
wants it cannot make you act on its
own only your choice to act makes you
act that's always on
you so you can have the pressure
building up building up but you are the
one who then chooses I can't take this
anymore let me do this this what I'm
pressured towards in other words the
compulsion to drink this poisonous
beverage is so much I don't care about
the poison but it always has to be your
choice cannot be just pressure
automatically comes and then the action
automatically follows pressure goes in one direction
follows pressure goes in one direction
action goes in another Direction You Are
The Binding
agent you are the one who does not want
the pressure and that's why chooses to
go the pathway of following the pleasure
to cover it up to replace it with the
intensity of this pressure is from the
point of view 3 years ago and now is of
course much less of course yeah cuz
you've been practicing restraint and
keeping the preset so you are not
fueling yeah but if you want to appro it
once and for all you have to recognize
cuz by the way the pressure is now
deintensified cuz you haven't been
living in world like
before so the
circumstances have diminished your
exposure to the pressuring things but if
you were to say be forced to return and
work and live like before would your
mind still remain
unbothered would you not would would
would Temptations not exist for
it that life is already diminished so
this B problem well it is diminished but
it's diminished because of the
circumstances
like the fact that see you you might
disagree but the fact is you still
doubtful about it which means you don't
know for sure you like to think it's
diminished and yet there is no problem
in thinking it's diminished but the
problem is to think that it's diminished
because of something that that it's not
there it can only diminish when the
danger becomes fully apparent and then
it doesn't matter the circumstances of
of course you would still prefer to live
a quiet life but if that changes War
comes you get put in a prison or
whatever the value of not drinking the
poison cannot
diminish and and for that value to be
fully developed you need to recognize
that no amount of pressure makes you act
you make yourself act because you don't
want the pressure because you want to
resist it because you want it to go
sooner that's why often those Those comp
similar in the sutas of arahan being
like the immovable Mountain it's not
that arahan doesn't experience the the
mountain doesn't experience the wind the
rain the snow the elements it does but
it's immovable that cannot make it act
and that's the Arun no amount of stuff
can make him do things out of GRE
diversion delusion impossible the the
connection has been severed the
association has been
destroyed so when arahant is
experiencing pressures of elements or
harassment there is no even an option
for his mind to like oh let me go back
to this desire to to give in to relieve
myself because he fully understood that
there is no relief in the way he used to
think he was like burning
embers they don't factually offer relief
from leprosy they just numb you down
because they burn
you doesn't mean so like the fact that
he cannot his mind he cannot choose
those actions it means exactly the opposite of
actions it means exactly the opposite of
it meaning like his choices are not free
anymore or something it's it's
completely the opposite it's like his
choice when you said that it's like
completely severed from those pressures
it makes that's what makes it utterly
free yeah because the you know there is
no reason like it's impossible for
somebody to willingly freely choose to
just burn themselves with that ember can
only be done kind of associating it with
the notion of relief from
what but if there is no original bother
from which you would be seeking the
relief there is no association for
acting for doing anything towards it so
if the
pressure doesn't matter the intensity
cannot bother
you why would you be breaking the prets
why would you be giving into anything on
counted it you only do so cuz it still bothers
you and it will bother you it's not like
that's going to stop
overnight but the reason why I'm saying
is this is so that you know then okay so
it's it's not that pressure
automatically results in
action it's more like I have a critical
point after which I can't withstand the
pressure and then I choose to to go this
way or that way which means that point
needs to be
upgraded that point needs to be
developed further whereby as the suta say even if
further whereby as the suta say even if
Highway robbers catch you and chop your
limbs off and abuse
you not just you wouldn't do anything by
body or speech out of that pressure even
mentally the Su says arant will not have
thoughts of hatred towards them cuz that
was already A coping mechanism hateful
thoughts but there is nothing to cope
why would you be coping when nothing is
bothering you to begin with
so the practical
way less and less acting out of pressure
is better Direction than
and acting out of pressure in direction
of
constant increasing so to speak so it's
so it's
like removing yourself from domain of
acting out of pressure by not giving
in instead of even those small acts of
acting out of pressure is like
still there is some burning of this fire
even little but still it bur yes yes in
in that theoretical sense that's correct
it's just
that what constitutes acting out of
pressure is not a static
thing that you can just adhere to it as
a
method what constitutes what's acting
out of pressure the time is your
intention to act at a
time so that's what needs to be refined
more and more so first you obviously
don't act out in the obvious course
visibly un wholesome
ways and when that basis is covered you
follow the same
principle and then you see whether
you're thing that you're about to do
even if it's not against the precepts
you see well where is this rooted
at am I doing it because of some of one
of the entrances
because of this because of that I want
to get rid of the discomfort of it in
which case you already recognize ah okay
so that will be rooted in pressure so
then when you say no to it your job
begins because often people think aha
okay so I just need to keep saying no to
the acting out of pressure and then sort
of party will
happen no learning how to say no out to
the pressure on the right level is way
your practice
starts cuz when you say no to acting out
of pressure even if it's not against the
precept for example well your mind will
let you know about it if not right away
it's going to start going in that
direction so it's going to start
throwing more rational thoughts at you
more irrational thoughts at you
irrational scenarios trying to scare you
more trying to pressure you more just
because you said no to those little
things and then what do you do do you
then explain that mind way do you focus
on your nostril so you don't have to
think about it do you try to distract
yourself with Garden work so that you
don't think about what's pressuring you
or do you allow it to be there because
that's what it is that's who it is
that's what the mind
is and then learn to live with that type
of mind let's put it that way not the
mind on your own
terms cuz see by learning to live with
it you're learning to not be moved by
any intensity of any scenario of any
mind state
and that's why technically as the WD was
saying this can be developed even if
somebody's outside of his
teaching obviously they would be very
wise and astute as to where the point is
but it's not limited this mind
development of course we know it now
because of the Buddhist teachings but
generally you could see if somebody for
whatever reason starts valuing not
acting out of pressure starts refining
the same principle but then not covering
up the mind that that's the result of
that imposed uh pressure and saying no
to your desires they would force
themselves to grow and become
immovable and sometimes that mind might
be in that state for days weeks state of
Doubt state of discomfort just mind
everything else is fine but in the back
of the mind you know like if something
bothers you and you have to wait 2 weeks
before you can resolve
it and some is really bothering you it's
an important thing but for two weeks you
have to be patient with
it so what your common person would do
they would just try to make those two
weeks go as quickly as possible engage
in sensuality engage in distraction
don't think about it until the second
week comes when you can deal with it but
now imagine you have no access to
sensuality or distractions you just have
to stay with something that will bother
you for Wow 14
days and not deny that
mind don't spend your whole day sleeping
so you don't think about it but go about
your life with this being the the the
the weather the mood always
there that's the that's the training of
of separating yourself correctly of
disassociating yourself from from that
mind correctly now imagine if you if
instead of two weeks you ready for 2
years 20 years forever
that's it you will be free from your own
mind if you're ready to be with it
forever without any traces of resistance
towards it or trying to replace it or
deal with it or distract yourself from
it there's nothing left for you to
do but yeah start with two
weeks cuz he doesn't you don't need to
do anything about when that states
present it's not like oh now I have to
do this and you don't have to do
anything you just have to say no to
doing things they will be taking you
away from
it that's how you stay with it
taking you away from it means becoming
absorbed in its content whatever
distracting yourself from it yeah psychologizing
yeah psychologizing
it focusing away moment to moment so you
don't think about it so it
disappears and then but it also doesn't
necessarily mean again must keep it
there no because that well that becomes
you're doing again it's on your own
terms so say you think I must keep it
there well you ask yourself why why do I
have to keep it there if I don't keep it
will it go away
no if I keep it will it go faster oh
well that's kind of what I'm hoping that
if I keep it there it will disappear and
stop bothering me cuz I'm resisting
it so not pushing forward not standing
still and as the suit
says and not pulling backwards as I
say so basically disown it that Mine by
not acting out disowning would be the
result of setting it up correctly and
then enduring it
correctly but if I say yes the son it
it's something that you you would
probably start to
do start applying the idea of dising it
but that's not dising
it dising means not feed it don't let it
disappear either I don't distract
yourself from
it that will result in disowning why
because it will become apparent that you
can't own it even if you want to e